<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="sub.haus/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="sub.haus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-03T15:41:06+00:00</updated><id>sub.haus/feed.xml</id><title type="html">SubHaus</title><subtitle>A haphazard collection of thoughts</subtitle><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><entry><title type="html">Rhys</title><link href="sub.haus/rhys/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rhys" /><published>2022-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>sub.haus/rhys</id><content type="html" xml:base="sub.haus/rhys/"><![CDATA[<p>I have written and deleted the start of this post more times than I care to admit this morning. It’s hard to encapsulate how I feel when the news that Rhys passed away is still so fresh.</p>

<p>I feel numb.</p>

<p>I posted to Twitter this morning with a photo of Rhys I took at the top of Grouse Mountain in Vancouver. He has been visiting us in our family home after spending a week at an IETF meeting downtown.</p>

<p>I made him hike his socks off on the North Shore with a trip around Lynn Creek and Lynn Valley/Mountain Highway, but rewarded him with a solid Canadian brunch. We followed that up with hiking the Grouse Grind and I think it’s fair to say I ruined his knees that day. The photo was taken just before our server brought out a couple of bottles of ice-cold beer that he used as a salve on his joints.</p>

<p>The kids loved having him around. He was always such easy company and great fun to be around. We are so much poorer for losing him.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/rhys.jpeg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have written and deleted the start of this post more times than I care to admit this morning. It’s hard to encapsulate how I feel when the news that Rhys passed away is still so fresh.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ski Camp</title><link href="sub.haus/Ski-Camp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ski Camp" /><published>2022-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>sub.haus/Ski-Camp</id><content type="html" xml:base="sub.haus/Ski-Camp/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m writing this post through a different lens than I would have done twenty-four hours ago.</p>

<p>With everything going on in the world at present, there is some guilt mixed in with the sheer joy of spending time with a bunch of youth at their Ski Camp this past weekend. We were lucky enough to be invited along to this one and I offered to help out with shifting gear to and from the hill as well as hanging around on the slopes.</p>

<p>It’s almost three years to the day since we last ran a camp for Scout-aged youth to test out their skiing skills on big mountain terrain. This past weekend saw a few of the Senior Scouts and their peers in Vents take to the slopes of Sunshine Ski Resort in Banff, AB.</p>

<p>As camps go, this kind of linking event was again a reminder of just how fortunate we are to be able to spend time guiding and mentoring these kids in activities they love to try and time they want to spend with each other. It’s a real privilege to see how much they have grown and developed as individuals and as a community during the most tumultuous times we have witnessed in generations.</p>

<p>Selfishly, it also meant that I had time with other adults who see the promise and purpose in giving up their time for these kids.</p>

<p>It is difficult to overstate just how very normal and understated the entire weekend was. These kids continue to grow up in a world that is so very different to that of my own youth and it is my firm belief that by providing them these opportunities is at least some route to normalcy.</p>

<div class="gallery" data-columns="1">
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0409.jpeg" />
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0413.jpeg" />
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0415.jpeg" />
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0416.jpeg" />
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0427.jpeg" />
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0431.jpeg" />
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0436.jpeg" />
	<img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0448.jpeg" />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m writing this post through a different lens than I would have done twenty-four hours ago.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winter Camping</title><link href="sub.haus/Winter-Camping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Camping" /><published>2022-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>sub.haus/Winter-Camping</id><content type="html" xml:base="sub.haus/Winter-Camping/"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend saw us out at Water Valley towards the foothills for our annual Winter Camp. Of course, being as Albertan weather tends to be winter when it feels like it, it was actually colder back in our November ‘Fall’ camp than we experienced just. No problem though. -16C overnight was cool enough to warrant the ‘winter’ experience and sufficiently warm enough not to impact us from having to retain social separation and all that goes along with remaining on the science-side of managing our response to COVID.</p>

<p>Ice Safety was the core theme to the weekend, given we were sat at the side of a large enough lake to offer a great risk landscape.  We took to the ice with an auger and talked over ice thickness for weight support and signs to watch for in ice conditions. It’s always intersting to see confidence grow in the skills we teach from those who are maybe just that little more nervous about trying something new.</p>

<p>Having a smaller showing of participants actually made for a more effective camp given there was a good ratio of skilled and experienced folks to new and less experienced kids.</p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last weekend saw us out at Water Valley towards the foothills for our annual Winter Camp. Of course, being as Albertan weather tends to be winter when it feels like it, it was actually colder back in our November ‘Fall’ camp than we experienced just. No problem though. -16C overnight was cool enough to warrant the ‘winter’ experience and sufficiently warm enough not to impact us from having to retain social separation and all that goes along with remaining on the science-side of managing our response to COVID.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Back To The Future</title><link href="sub.haus/Back-to-the-Future/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Back To The Future" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>sub.haus/Back-to-the-Future</id><content type="html" xml:base="sub.haus/Back-to-the-Future/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve decided to resurrect the Breadedcod.com site after a fairly lengthy hiatus. I can’t even remember when the old Wordpress blog went by the wayside, but it’s quite some time ago. *I just checked, it’s been a few years according to the ol’ reliable of archive.org.</p>

<p>Anyway, ‘HI!’ again, for those of you who may have happened upon me before, and welcome to anyone else who might be here as a new reader or passive observer. Eye-rollers are also welcome. Even occasional tutters.</p>

<h4 id="reasons-to-be-digitally-cheerful">Reasons to be (digitally) cheerful.</h4>

<p>One of the main reasons for me to slap all this back together is because I’m so done with trying (and failing) to make Facebook or other social platforms actually work for me in a way that’s conducive to either getting things out of my head and on paper or in building positive relationships with new people.</p>

<p>All those social megavendors are just massive digital landfills to me now. I actually rejoined Facebook in a limited capacity because of the pandemic, after swearing off it and going dark. It feels like a mistake being back there. I love the fact I’m reconnected with some folks from my old friend list (although it is heavily curated now). The problems that were apparent a couple of years ago haven’t improved though. It feels even more polarised than ever. It’s almost like people are trapped in there and are trying desperately to keep going while ignoring the rot going on all around them.</p>

<p>I am going to sound incredibly old with all of this - likely because I <em>am</em>, in internet years at least. In those <em>old</em> days of the internet, I have met some truly amazing people. Some have become close friends and the opportunities that were opened up through meeting them changed my life. That’s what I hope to recapture here and hopefully help others find along the way too.</p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve decided to resurrect the Breadedcod.com site after a fairly lengthy hiatus. I can’t even remember when the old Wordpress blog went by the wayside, but it’s quite some time ago. *I just checked, it’s been a few years according to the ol’ reliable of archive.org.]]></summary></entry></feed>