<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sub.haus/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://sub.haus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-14T22:57:42+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/feed.xml</id><title type="html">SubHaus</title><subtitle>A haphazard collection of thoughts</subtitle><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><entry><title type="html">The satellites that never sleep how we keep an eye on earth</title><link href="https://sub.haus/2025/03/14/The-Satellites-That-Never-Sleep-How-We-Keep-an-Eye-on-Earth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The satellites that never sleep how we keep an eye on earth" /><published>2025-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/2025/03/14/The%20Satellites%20That%20Never%20Sleep%20-%20How%20We%20Keep%20an%20Eye%20on%20Earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sub.haus/2025/03/14/The-Satellites-That-Never-Sleep-How-We-Keep-an-Eye-on-Earth/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s something rather humbling about standing in your back garden on a clear Calgary night, staring up at the stars with a mug of tea gone cold in your hands, and suddenly spotting that telltale streak of light moving steadily across the heavens. Not a shooting star, mind you, but one of humanity’s own creations — a satellite, silently and irreverently going about its business.</p>

<p>I had such a moment last week. While my dog watches me with that particularly Labrador brand of food-obsessed disdain reserved for humans engaged in seemingly pointless activities, I tracked what I’m fairly certain was the International Space Station with my smartphone app. This got me thinking about all those mechanical eyes we’ve placed in orbit, keeping constant watch over our humble blue marble—some of which I had the privilege of working on in my younger days.</p>

<h2 id="an-orbital-traffic-jam">An Orbital Traffic Jam</h2>

<p>If you’ve ever thought the Trans-Canada Highway during a long weekend was crowded, consider this: at this very moment, there are over 7,500 satellites orbiting our planet. That’s more than all the cattle in the average Alberta ranch, and considerably less cooperative when it comes to herding them.</p>

<p>The number is staggering when you consider that before 1957, there were precisely zero human-made objects circling our planet. Sputnik changed all that with its now-quaint “beep beep” signal, and we’ve been enthusiastically cluttering Earth’s vicinity ever since.</p>

<p>SpaceX alone has launched over 5,000 Starlink satellites, creating a constellation that occasionally photobombs astronomers’ careful observations of distant galaxies. I imagine these astronomers shaking their fists at the sky, much like I do when someone parks their F-250 across two spaces at Save-On.</p>

<h2 id="the-constant-watchers">The Constant Watchers</h2>

<h2 id="from-researcher-to-observer">From Researcher to Observer</h2>

<p>What fascinates me most about these orbiting machines is that they neither sleep nor blink. Having worked on missions like CNES POLDER, SPOT-VGT, NASA MODIS, and CHRIS-PROBA as a young researcher, I gained more than an intimate appreciation for their relentless data collection. While I’m now struggling to keep my eyes open during a particularly dull MS Teams meeting, these Earth observation satellites are diligently recording everything from crop yields in Kansas to illegal logging in the Amazon.</p>

<p>Weather satellites are perhaps the most immediately useful to those of us in Calgary, where the weather can swing from a pleasant 20°C to a snowstorm within hours. These faithful watchers give meteorologists the data they need to tell us, with increasing accuracy, that yes, it will indeed snow during our planned camp at the weekend — a particularly Canadian predicament.</p>

<p>The European Space Agency’s Sentinel satellites, part of the Copernicus program, continuously monitor everything from air quality to sea surface temperatures. When I worked as a researcher on those 90s platforms, we were collecting crucial data on global vegetation patterns and energy balances. Practical applications for EO data were still somewhat stuck in the realms of specialist science. Today, when I’m grumbling about the wildfire smoke drifting into Calgary from British Columbia during summer months, satellites are tracking its spread and concentration, providing data that helps shape public health responses and environmental policies.</p>

<h2 id="when-satellites-save-lives">When Satellites Save Lives</h2>

<p>It’s easy to make light of these technologies until you realize their profound impact. In 2022, when devastating floods hit Pakistan, satellite imagery provided crucial information for rescue operations, helping to coordinate efforts in regions where ground communications had been destroyed.</p>

<p>Closer to home, the same technology tracks changes in our own landscape. The retreating glaciers in the Canadian Rockies that I am fortunate enough to have in my local back yard, the recovery of forests after the devastating wildfires in Fort McMurray, the shifting patterns of urban development as Calgary sprawls outward—all captured by these tireless observers, some of which use technologies and methods I had the tiniest bit of good fortune in helping develop during my earlier career.</p>

<p>It’s quite poignant that, as our planet grapples with unprecedented environmental challenges, we’ve entrusted these mechanical guardians to watch over it, meticulously documenting changes that are too subtle for us to notice daily but have devastating cumulative effects.</p>

<h2 id="a-personal-perspective">A Personal Perspective</h2>

<h2 id="from-theory-to-practice">From Theory to Practice</h2>

<p>I’m old enough to remember when satellite TV first arrived in our Yorkshire neighbourhood growing up. The family of a friend of mine installed a dish that seemed comically large, and looked like it was more useful for attempting to communicate with another planet. In the age of Hubble and the Space Shuttle, satellite still seemed novel and far removed from anything I would be exposed to. Little did I know then that I would later be working on MODIS and other Earth observation missions, helping design systems that would capture data used by scientists worldwide.</p>

<p>The democratization of satellite data has been even more remarkable than I ever anticipated during my research days. The MODIS data I once worked with, which required specialized knowledge and systems to process, is now accessible to anyone with an internet connection – at least for now. Despite being an ‘insider’ in the early days, I’ve still spent an embarrassing amount of time looking at where I have lived over the years, trying to determine if that really is our old car or the kids’ trampoline in the yard.</p>

<h2 id="the-future-above-us">The Future Above Us</h2>

<p>As we look to the future, the role of these orbital observers will only grow. New generations of satellites with increasingly sophisticated sensors will provide even more detailed data about our world. Small satellites called CubeSats, some no larger than a loaf of bread (though considerably less tasty), are making space more accessible to universities and even schools.</p>

<p>Climate monitoring will become even more crucial as we navigate the challenges of global warming. When I was working on the POLDER mission, we were just beginning to understand how satellite data could track environmental changes. Today’s satellites monitor carbon emissions, forest cover, and ice melt with unprecedented precision, holding us accountable in ways we really shouldn’t be able to ignore and yet somehow manage to. The evolution from the instruments I worked with to today’s capabilities has been nothing short of remarkable.</p>

<p>And perhaps, as these digital eyes continue to watch over us, they’ll help us gain a new perspective on our planet—not as separate nations divided by borders and tariffs invisible from orbit, but as a single, fragile ecosystem that sustains us all.</p>

<p>For now, though, I’ll continue my occasional backyard stargazing in Calgary, mug of tea in hand, watching for those moving points of light and contemplating my journey from a young researcher working on satellite missions to someone who now simply appreciates their silent passage overhead.</p>

<p>My professional experience has given me a unique perspective on these eyes in the sky, but there’s still something magical about spotting them from my backyard. Just don’t tell my dog. Having witnessed me excitedly pointing out that “I worked on that one!” whenever certain satellites pass overhead, she already thinks I’m strange enough - and that’s pretty rich coming from a Labrador.</p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s something rather humbling about standing in your back garden on a clear Calgary night, staring up at the stars with a mug of tea gone cold in your hands, and suddenly spotting that telltale streak of light moving steadily across the heavens. Not a shooting star, mind you, but one of humanity’s own creations — a satellite, silently and irreverently going about its business.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Echoes and effects of the covid 19 pandemic on youth (redux)</title><link href="https://sub.haus/2025/03/04/Echoes-and-Effects-of-the-COVID-19-Pandemic-on-Youth-(Redux)/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes and effects of the covid 19 pandemic on youth (redux)" /><published>2025-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/2025/03/04/Echoes%20and%20Effects%20of%20the%20COVID-19%20Pandemic%20on%20Youth%20(Redux)</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sub.haus/2025/03/04/Echoes-and-Effects-of-the-COVID-19-Pandemic-on-Youth-(Redux)/"><![CDATA[<p>As a few of us ex-Westjetters were heading to grab coffee the other morning, it suddenly struck me that we are fast approaching half a decade since the onset of the COVID-19 Pandemic.</p>

<p>Half. A. Decade.</p>

<p>It doesn’t seem real that so much time has already passed.</p>

<p>Related to that, this article originally appeared on my LinkedIn profile back in 2023. I’ve liberated it from there and re-homed it here for posterity, but also in case I decide to pull the pin on ditching LinkedIn to the same recycle bin as every other social network.</p>

<p>As we see, in real time, global forces pushing for deepening isolationism and exceptionalism, I stand by what I wrote back then. Connection now, more than ever, is vital for our global wellbeing – especially in a world dominated by attention thief apps and misinformation.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>With so little media attention now focussed on the COVID-19 pandemic it feels like we have closed the book on the past few years and moved on. It can be both a little jarring and equally as hazy to think back just two three years to the summer of 2020 and what life was like at the time. The pandemic unleashed a relentless storm upon our world, leaving no corner untouched by its far-reaching consequences, but have we really taken stock of how much the impacts have created running issues today.</p>

<p>From the shattered economies to the frayed social fabric, it was a global crisis that challenged us in unprecedented ways, particularly and somewhat annoyingly in the overuse of the word unprecedented. We continue to grapple with the aftermath as global recovery is stymied by economic pressures that have further exacerbated inequalities across society. The pandemic’s impact continues to reverberate across industries, communities, and individual lives, occasionally still reminding us of our shared vulnerability.</p>

<p>Amidst the carnage caused by the COVID-19 pandemic, one group that has been particularly affected stands out: our youth. They have borne the weight of disrupted education, shattered dreams, and isolated realities perhaps more than any other generational group.</p>

<p>The absence of adventure and the longing for connection has left an indelible mark on their well-being and personal growth. As we emerge from the darkness of the pandemic, we must recognize the profound need to reignite our spirits with the flames of adventure and reconnection.</p>

<p>As a volunteer Scouter Leader in Canada for the past decade I have had the privilege of holding a front-row seat to seeing hundreds of youth grow in size, skills and confidence from the youngest sections of Beaver Scouts through to Young Adults. The pandemic was just as much of an impact on our activities in Scouts as it was on the professional lives of all of our volunteers. It was no secret that we struggled with the abrupt shift to meetings being virtual and immediately lost our ability to meet in person for weekly adventures.</p>

<p>Beyond mere leisure or entertainment, these vital experiences hold the power to heal, inspire, and empower young individuals. By providing them with opportunities to explore, engage, and form meaningful connections, we can cultivate their resilience, expand their horizons, and equip them with the essential tools they need to navigate a future still subject to continued ‘aftershocks’.</p>

<h2 id="the-effects-of-the-pandemic-on-youth-and-the-need-for-reconnection">The Effects of the Pandemic On Youth and The Need For Reconnection</h2>

<p>As the pandemic swept across the world, its marked impact was keenly felt within our Troop of Scouts. The immediate effects were disorienting and profound. Overnight, the vibrant faces that usually came together for weekly adventures were reduced to pixelated images on a screen. The shared laughter, the collective learning, and the tangible camaraderie that formed the bedrock of our meetings were replaced by an eerie silence and a sense of isolation. Our young Scouts, accustomed to the open skies, the thrill of adventure, and the joy of shared experiences, found themselves confined within the four walls of their homes, grappling with the sudden onset of the digital era in Scouting.</p>

<p>More broadly, however, it is understood that these impacts were not an isolated experience. The impacts on youth included:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Mental Health: Numerous studies have examined the increased prevalence of mental health challenges, such as anxiety and depression, among young people during the pandemic. Research conducted by Loades et al. (2020) and Racine et al. (2020) shed light on the psychological impact of the pandemic on children and adolescents.</li>
  <li>Disruption to Education: Research carried out by UNESCO (2020) and the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) has explored the disruption of education systems and the potential long-term consequences for academic achievement, learning gaps, and social-emotional development.</li>
  <li>Social Isolation and Loneliness: The effects of social distancing and limited social interactions on the mental well-being of young individuals have been investigated by studies such as Oosterhoff et al. (2020) and Cooper et al. (2021), emphasizing the heightened risk of loneliness and its impact on youth.</li>
  <li>Loss of Milestones and Experiences: Research conducted by Elmer et al. (2020) and Margolies et al. (2020) has delved into the emotional and developmental consequences of missing out on significant milestones and experiences, such as graduations, proms, extracurricular activities, and social gatherings.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-importance-of-adventure-for-youth">The Importance of Adventure For Youth</h2>

<p>Adventure and exploration play a crucial role in the holistic development of youth, offering a wide range of significant benefits. Let’s explore the key aspects of their significance:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Personal Growth: Adventure and exploration provide young individuals with invaluable opportunities to step out of their comfort zones, face challenges, and develop essential life skills. Engaging in new experiences cultivates self-confidence, resilience, and adaptability, empowering youth to navigate unfamiliar situations and overcome obstacles.</li>
  <li>Broadening Perspectives: Adventure and exploration expose young people to diverse cultures, environments, and viewpoints. By venturing beyond familiar surroundings, they gain a broader understanding of the world, fostering empathy, cultural appreciation, and a global mindset.</li>
  <li>Skill Development: Adventure activities often involve acquiring practical skills such as problem-solving, decision-making, teamwork, and leadership. These skills are transferable to various aspects of life, including education, career, and personal relationships.</li>
  <li>Physical Health and Well-being: Adventure and exploration encourage physical activity and healthy lifestyles. Whether it’s hiking, biking, or engaging in water sports, these activities promote physical fitness, enhance motor skills, and contribute to overall well-being.</li>
  <li>Mental and Emotional Well-being: Immersion in nature, outdoor activities, and novel experiences have been linked to improved mental health. Adventure and exploration provide a respite from the pressures of daily life, reducing stress, boosting mood, and fostering feelings of happiness and fulfillment.</li>
  <li>Connection with Nature: Adventure and exploration often take place in outdoor settings, allowing youth to connect with nature and develop a sense of environmental stewardship. This connection fosters an appreciation for the natural world, instilling a desire to protect and conserve the environment.</li>
  <li>Creativity and Innovation: Engaging in adventurous pursuits stimulates creativity and nurtures innovative thinking. Exploring new environments and solving challenges outside of conventional settings sparks imaginative problem-solving and cultivates a mindset of curiosity and experimentation.</li>
  <li>Building Social Bonds: Adventure and exploration can be shared experiences, fostering social connections and forming lasting friendships. Collaborative activities encourage teamwork, cooperation, and effective communication, while group dynamics promote social skills and empathy.</li>
</ol>

<p>Overall, adventure and exploration weave together a tapestry of experiences that contribute to the holistic development of youth, nurturing their personal growth, expanding their horizons, and equipping them with the skills and mindset needed to navigate the complexities of life.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.licdn.com/dms/image/v2/D5612AQF5iqXKKPW_oA/article-inline_image-shrink_1000_1488/article-inline_image-shrink_1000_1488/0/1689458087009?e=1746662400&amp;v=beta&amp;t=SZ93E3236pwfuZ8OS5QrAh9xvNuznKKQEVRz4cJUMU8" alt="The shot shows a classic deflagrated u-shaped valley in the Alps.  The Scouts are making their way up the valley weighed down with full packs of clothes, food and water for an overnight adventure at high elevation." /></p>

<p>Hiking in the high Alpine on our way to an overnight stop.</p>

<h2 id="the-power-of-reconnection">The Power of Reconnection</h2>

<p>Reestablishing connections and nurturing social relationships post-pandemic is vital for young individuals due to several compelling reasons:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Emotional Well-being: As social beings, humans thrive on connections, which are essential for emotional well-being. After enduring prolonged periods of isolation and limited social interactions during the pandemic, young people may have experienced feelings of loneliness, anxiety, and depression. Reconnecting with others not only offers emotional support but also provides a sense of belonging, helping to alleviate these negative emotions.</li>
  <li>Mental Health: Strong social bonds have a profound impact on mental health. By reconnecting with friends, family, and the community, young individuals can cultivate a support system that fosters understanding, empathy, and encouragement. Sharing experiences, thoughts, and emotions with others helps to reduce stress, boost self-esteem, and improve overall mental well-being.</li>
  <li>Sense of Belonging: Rebuilding social bonds enables young people to regain a sense of belonging and connection to their communities. Feeling part of a social network provides a sense of identity, purpose, and shared values. It enhances self-confidence and self-worth, fostering a positive sense of identity and a feeling of being valued and accepted.</li>
  <li>Opportunities for Growth: Reconnecting with others presents opportunities for personal growth and development. Through interactions with diverse individuals, young people can learn from different perspectives, broaden their knowledge, and develop their social skills, empathy, and understanding of others. Meaningful connections can open doors to new experiences, ideas, and opportunities for learning and personal enrichment.</li>
  <li>Collaboration and Support: Rebuilding social bonds allows for collaboration and mutual support. Working together with others on shared goals or projects fosters teamwork, cooperation, and the exchange of knowledge and resources. Social connections provide a network of support during challenging times, offering guidance, advice, and assistance when needed.</li>
</ol>

<p>In summary, young individuals yearn to reconnect with others and rebuild social bonds beyond the pandemic to enhance their emotional well-being, support their mental health, foster a sense of belonging, facilitate personal growth, and build valuable social and professional networks. We witnessed this firsthand in our Troop. These connections provide a sense of community, offer support, and contribute to their overall happiness and fulfillment in life.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.licdn.com/dms/image/v2/D5612AQFJ6t8rr-UgXQ/article-inline_image-shrink_1000_1488/article-inline_image-shrink_1000_1488/0/1689458465166?e=1746662400&amp;v=beta&amp;t=Od6IjcovaZZzZwz2gKrRjtEbIGUwAoHhOPw8cRjmwvg" alt="The large campfire area at KISC is a semi-circular amphitheatre constructed of large stone slabs with a main stage and fire ring at the front. There are a number of groups present in brightly-coloured shirts and with they own unique neckerchiefs or scarves." /></p>

<p>The International Campfire at Kandersteg attended by groups from around the world.</p>

<h2 id="overcoming-challenges-and-embracing-opportunities">Overcoming Challenges and Embracing Opportunities</h2>

<p>Planning adventures and reconnection opportunities during the recovery from the pandemic has been a continuous source of challenges and setbacks, especially when it involves large groups. However, we collectively agreed on the need for an audacious goal: to create a memorable experience for the Scouts who had missed out on so many opportunities in their first two years of the program. With this in mind, we decided to take a group of young people to the <a href="https://kisc.ch/">Kandersteg International Scouting Centre</a> in Switzerland.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.licdn.com/dms/image/v2/D5612AQHhkUCjAHZJwQ/article-inline_image-shrink_1000_1488/article-inline_image-shrink_1000_1488/0/1689458024634?e=1746662400&amp;v=beta&amp;t=9Ux9B_99a2Dt2MqqdahqZwLgWf0H-7J6lok7FPjnUtA" alt="A selfie of a Scout and Leader from the 31st St Cyprian's Scouts, Calgary. They are sitting on the lawn in from of the Kandersteg International Scout Centre's main Swiss Chalet." /></p>

<p>Waiting to check-in to camp after a mammoth journey across the globe</p>

<p>Nothing comes easily for small non-profit groups, even in “normal times”. Even when it comes to travelling to international destinations supported by professional Travel Agents, we faced several challenges. These difficulties arose due to ongoing uncertainties and restrictions related to the pandemic. Some of the key challenges we encountered included:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Travel Restrictions: Many countries continued to impose travel restrictions, such as entry requirements, quarantine protocols, and vaccination mandates. These restrictions can make it challenging to plan and execute international group travel, as they may vary from one destination to another and change frequently, even at home.</li>
  <li>Health and Safety Concerns: The health and safety of individuals remained a top priority. The risk of COVID-19 transmission and the potential for new variants posed challenges to organizing group travel, particularly in crowded environments or high-risk areas. Ensuring the well-being of participants and adhering to health guidelines required additional planning and precautions.</li>
  <li>Uncertain Timelines: The recovery from the pandemic was an ongoing process, and the timeline for full normalization remained (remains?) uncertain. Planning long-term adventures or reconnection opportunities required flexibility and the ability to adapt to changing circumstances, as restrictions and guidelines can shift with evolving pandemic conditions.</li>
  <li>Financial Considerations: The financial implications of organizing large group travel were substantial. Factors such as potential cancellations, changes in travel restrictions, and fluctuating costs impacted budgeting and financial viability on several occasions, especially with a number of our regular fundraising opportunities still being in hibernation because of the pandemic.</li>
  <li>Logistics and Coordination: Organizing group travel involves intricate logistics and coordination, which became more challenging during the pandemic recovery. Transport, accommodation, activities, and other arrangements required careful planning to ensure compliance with health and safety guidelines and the ability to respond to any unforeseen circumstances.</li>
  <li>Stakeholder Communication: Effective communication with participants, partners, and stakeholders is crucial during the planning process. Keeping everyone informed about travel restrictions, health protocols, and potential changes in travel plans or arrangements required clear and timely communication channels.</li>
  <li>Moral and Ethical Considerations: While planning adventures and reconnection opportunities, it was important to consider the moral and ethical aspects of travel during the pandemic recovery. Assessing the potential risks and weighing the benefits against the health and safety of participants, local communities, and the destination itself is essential to make responsible and informed decisions.</li>
</ol>

<p>Reflecting on the challenges we faced as a dedicated group of volunteers, Scouts, and parents, I am reminded of the immense time and effort we invested. It truly was a monumental undertaking, comparable to the grandeur of an alpine peak.</p>

<p><img src="https://media.licdn.com/dms/image/v2/D5612AQEEOKSlhGsC0A/article-inline_image-shrink_1500_2232/article-inline_image-shrink_1500_2232/0/1689458189343?e=1746662400&amp;v=beta&amp;t=IDEEWorqqpx4dwYnyG0ZTXTyiorFeEz2HY7la4N91wQ" alt="An airbus wingtip shot with the snow-covered peak of Mount Baker, WA in the background." /></p>

<p>Back in Canada and a perfect view of Mt Baker on our way out of Vancouver.</p>

<p>Now, a year has passed since we departed for Kandersteg, and I am filled with pride for the flawless execution of our plan. We provided our Scouts with the reconnection and adventure opportunities they so greatly deserved. Upon our return to Canada, we received heartfelt gratitude from both Scouts and parents. However, it was the simple feedback from one Scout, as they left the airport with their parents, that hit home instantly: “That was one of the best weeks of my life.”</p>

<p>Mission accomplished.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>When reflecting on the impact of the pandemic on young people and their need for adventure and reconnection, valuable lessons emerge for companies in how they treat their staff. Just as youth have faced disruption and isolation, employees too have experienced significant challenges and upheaval in their professional lives. Companies must recognize the importance of fostering a sense of adventure and reconnection within their workforce. It’s not as simple as mandating people back to the office and expecting everything to be as it was pre-pandemic.</p>

<p>It entails, at the very least, providing opportunities for personal growth, supporting mental well-being, and creating a positive and inclusive work environment that encourages social interactions and collaboration. By prioritizing the needs of their employees and nurturing a culture that embraces adventure and reconnection, companies can not only enhance employee satisfaction and productivity, but also cultivate resilience, creativity, and innovation within their teams.</p>

<p>As we move past the most recent pandemic, let us apply these lessons to ensure that companies prioritize the well-being and holistic development of their staff, empowering them to thrive and make a meaningful impact in their professional lives. Volunteering can be an incredibly rewarding experience and serve as a valuable counterpoint to professional work. Working with young people also offers a rich learning opportunity that is often underestimated in terms of professional development. After all, these young individuals are the future customers and employees. Investing a few hours a week in your community shouldn’t be too challenging, considering the potential benefits it can bring.</p>

<p>Let us seize the opportunity to learn, grow, and create a better future together.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<p>Loades, Maria Elizabeth, et al. “Rapid systematic review: the impact of social isolation and loneliness on the mental health of children and adolescents in the context of COVID-19.” Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry 59.11 (2020): 1218-1239.</p>

<p>Racine, Nicole, et al. “Child and adolescent mental illness during COVID-19: A rapid review.” Psychiatry Research 292 (2020): 113307</p>

<p>Oosterhoff, Benjamin, et al. “Adolescents’ motivations to engage in social distancing during the COVID-19 pandemic: associations with mental and social health.” <em>Journal of Adolescent Health</em> 67.2 (2020): 179-185.</p>

<p>Cooper, Kate, et al. “Loneliness, social relationships, and mental health in adolescents during the COVID-19 pandemic.” <em>Journal of Affective Disorders</em> 289 (2021): 98-104.</p>

<p>Elmer, Timon, Kieran Mepham, and Christoph Stadtfeld. “Students under lockdown: Comparisons of students’ social networks and mental health before and during the COVID-19 crisis in Switzerland.” <em>Plos one</em> 15.7 (2020): e0236337.</p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a few of us ex-Westjetters were heading to grab coffee the other morning, it suddenly struck me that we are fast approaching half a decade since the onset of the COVID-19 Pandemic.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Chose Obsidian.</title><link href="https://sub.haus/2025/03/03/Why-I-Chose-Obsidian" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Chose Obsidian." /><published>2025-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/2025/03/03/Why-I-Chose-Obsidian.</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sub.haus/2025/03/03/Why-I-Chose-Obsidian"><![CDATA[<h1 id="why-i-chose-obsidian-from-pandemic-discovery-to-daily-driver">Why I Chose Obsidian: From Pandemic Discovery to Daily Driver</h1>

<p>When the pandemic hit in early 2020, like many of us, I suddenly found myself with an abundance of unexpected free time.  With no real expectation that I would be returning to the role I was stood down from, I decided it was probably time to replace my aging (2011) Mac Mini and have something a bit more robust to work on, assuming that I might both be job hunting and/or working remote for the most part. This increased multi-mode digital dependency pushed me to evaluate the tools I was using daily. Building out a new workstation with bunch of different operating systems on it led me to need to solve the issue of a writing environment that was both multi-platform and available offline. Among these tools, perhaps none has had a more profound impact on my productivity and thinking than Obsidian.</p>

<h2 id="the-pre-obsidian-landscape">The Pre-Obsidian Landscape</h2>

<p>Before discovering Obsidian, my note-taking had taken me through several popular options:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>OneNote</strong>: Great for organization but lacking in plain text portability</li>
  <li><strong>Apple Notes</strong>: Seamless across Apple devices but limiting in advanced features</li>
  <li><strong>Evernote</strong>: Once the gold standard, but became bloated and subscription-heavy</li>
  <li><strong>Various markdown editors</strong>: Loved the simplicity but missed the interconnectedness</li>
</ul>

<p>Each tool had its strengths, but none quite captured what I was looking for: a lightweight, future-proof system that could connect ideas rather than just store them.</p>

<h2 id="finding-obsidian-during-lockdown">Finding Obsidian During Lockdown</h2>

<p>In mid-2020, amid endless Teams, Zoom calls and sourdough attempts, I stumbled upon Obsidian. What initially caught my attention wasn’t just another feature list, but a fundamentally different approach to knowledge management:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Local-first storage</strong>: My notes are mine, stored as plain text files on my computer</li>
  <li><strong>Markdown-based</strong>: Simple, portable, and future-proof formatting</li>
  <li><strong>Bi-directional linking</strong>: The ability to connect notes and discover relationships between ideas</li>
  <li><strong>Graph view</strong>: Visualizing my knowledge network in a way that revealed unexpected connections</li>
</ol>

<p>The concept of a “second brain” resonated with me immediately, primarily because the first brain was struggling with the (un)reality of living through a modern day global pandemic at the time. Instead of fighting against an application’s structure, Obsidian seemed to adapt to how my mind naturally worked - or at least could keep up with it without losing fidelity in scraps of post-it notes, paper, Word docs, emails, etc.</p>

<h2 id="the-learning-curve-worth-climbing">The Learning Curve Worth Climbing</h2>

<p>I won’t pretend the transition was effortless. Coming from more structured tools like OneNote, I initially found the blank canvas of Obsidian intimidating. How should I organize things? What folders should I create? What metadata would be useful?</p>

<p>But this initial friction forced me to think deeply about my note-taking system rather than accepting someone else’s predetermined structure. Over time, I developed a system that worked specifically for me:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Daily notes as entry points</li>
  <li>Topic-based folders for reference material</li>
  <li>Project-specific vaults for focused work</li>
  <li>Tags for cross-cutting themes</li>
</ul>

<p>The beauty of Obsidian is that it allowed this system to evolve organically as my needs changed.</p>

<h2 id="from-notes-to-networked-thinking">From Notes to Networked Thinking</h2>

<p>The real transformation came when I stopped thinking of Obsidian as just a note-taking app and started seeing it as a thinking environment. The connections between notes became as valuable as the notes themselves.</p>

<p>I began to notice patterns in my thinking, rediscover forgotten ideas, and make connections that wouldn’t have been possible in a linear note-taking system. Ideas from a book I read months ago would suddenly connect with a current project. Meeting notes would link to relevant research. Personal reflections would connect to professional insights.</p>

<p>This networked thinking fundamentally changed how I approached problems and projects.</p>

<h2 id="the-daily-driver-experience">The Daily Driver Experience</h2>

<p>Today, Obsidian has become my digital home base. It’s where I:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Plan my day with daily notes</li>
  <li>Draft emails and messages before sending them</li>
  <li>Outline presentations and articles</li>
  <li>Track project progress</li>
  <li>Capture meeting notes</li>
  <li>Store reference material and research</li>
  <li>Reflect on personal and professional growth</li>
</ul>

<p>The extensibility through plugins has allowed me to adapt the tool to my specific workflows rather than adapting my workflows to the tool.</p>

<h2 id="beyond-notes-blogging-from-obsidian">Beyond Notes: Blogging from Obsidian</h2>

<p>Which brings me to my current experiment: using Obsidian not just for private notes but for public writing. This very blog post is being written in Obsidian before being published to this Jekyll-powered GitHub Pages site.</p>

<p>The hypothesis I’m testing is whether staying in this familiar environment—with its linked references, embedded notes, and customized workflow—will help maintain a regular cadence of blog posts.</p>

<p>The advantages so far are clear:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Reduced friction</strong>: Writing happens in the same environment where my ideas develop</li>
  <li><strong>Rich context</strong>: Access to all my linked notes and references while writing</li>
  <li><strong>Consistent workflow</strong>: Using the same tools for both private thinking and public sharing</li>
  <li><strong>Future-proof format</strong>: Markdown files that can be used anywhere</li>
</ul>

<p>The publishing workflow is straightforward: write in Obsidian, export/copy to my Jekyll blog repository, push to GitHub, and the post is live. I’d say that the simplicity of this process removes many of the barriers that previously prevented me from posting regularly - but that would be an outright lie. I could have gone to Wordpress at any point to pick up on blogging again, but honestly, these past few years haven’t really been conducive to that. I’m sure there’s a “Dead Internet” post due from me in the near future along those lines.</p>

<h2 id="the-bigger-picture-tools-that-think-with-you">The Bigger Picture: Tools That Think With You</h2>

<p>My journey with Obsidian reflects a broader shift in how we think about productivity tools. The best tools aren’t just containers for information; they’re environments that enhance how we think.</p>

<p>What makes Obsidian special isn’t just its feature set but its philosophy:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Knowledge should be connected, not just collected</li>
  <li>Tools should adapt to your thinking, not vice versa</li>
  <li>Your data should be yours in formats that will stand the test of time</li>
  <li>Simplicity and depth can coexist</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’re still using notes apps that feel like digital filing cabinets rather than thinking environments, I’d encourage you to give Obsidian a try. The learning curve is real, but so is the payoff.</p>

<h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>

<p>As I continue this experiment of blogging from Obsidian, I’m excited to see how it impacts not just the frequency of posts but their quality and interconnectedness. Will the networked thinking that’s been so valuable for my private notes translate to more insightful public writing?</p>

<p>That’s a hypothesis worth testing, and one I’ll report back on in future posts. For now, I’m grateful to have found a tool that’s not just helping me store information but helping me think better—during a pandemic and beyond.</p>

<p>The only other thing that I’ve been wanting to test out is whether or not I could get Mermaid to behave well from within Obsidian and straight to Jekyll posts. It took some wrangling to get this built out appropriately, but if you’re seeing a flowchart or two below, then it’s been a success. More on that later.</p>

<hr />

<p>Here’s a simple flowchart:</p>

<pre><code class="language-mermaid">graph TD;
    A[Obsidian] --&gt;|exports to| B[Jekyll];
    B --&gt; C{MermaidJS Support};
    C --&gt;|Working| D[Success];
    C --&gt;|Broken| E[Fix It!];
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="language-mermaid">graph TD;
    A --&gt; B;
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Chose Obsidian: From Pandemic Discovery to Daily Driver]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rhys</title><link href="https://sub.haus/2022/03/07/rhys/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rhys" /><published>2022-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/2022/03/07/rhys</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sub.haus/2022/03/07/rhys/"><![CDATA[<p>I have written and deleted the start of this post more times than I care to admit this morning. It’s hard to encapsulate how I feel when the news that Rhys passed away is still so fresh.</p>

<p>I feel numb.</p>

<p>I posted to Twitter this morning with a photo of Rhys I took at the top of Grouse Mountain in Vancouver. He has been visiting us in our family home after spending a week at an IETF meeting downtown.</p>

<p>I made him hike his socks off on the North Shore with a trip around Lynn Creek and Lynn Valley/Mountain Highway, but rewarded him with a solid Canadian brunch. We followed that up with hiking the Grouse Grind and I think it’s fair to say I ruined his knees that day. The photo was taken just before our server brought out a couple of bottles of ice-cold beer that he used as a salve on his joints.</p>

<p>The kids loved having him around. He was always such easy company and great fun to be around. We are so much poorer for losing him.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/rhys.jpeg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have written and deleted the start of this post more times than I care to admit this morning. It’s hard to encapsulate how I feel when the news that Rhys passed away is still so fresh.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ski Camp</title><link href="https://sub.haus/2022/03/06/Ski-Camp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ski Camp" /><published>2022-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/2022/03/06/Ski-Camp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sub.haus/2022/03/06/Ski-Camp/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m writing this post through a different lens than I would have done twenty-four hours ago.</p>

<p>With everything going on in the world at present, there is some guilt mixed in with the sheer joy of spending time with a bunch of youth at their Ski Camp this past weekend. We were lucky enough to be invited along to this one and I offered to help out with shifting gear to and from the hill as well as hanging around on the slopes.</p>

<p>It’s almost three years to the day since we last ran a camp for Scout-aged youth to test out their skiing skills on big mountain terrain. This past weekend saw a few of the Senior Scouts and their peers in Vents take to the slopes of Sunshine Ski Resort in Banff, AB.</p>

<p>As camps go, this kind of linking event was again a reminder of just how fortunate we are to be able to spend time guiding and mentoring these kids in activities they love to try and time they want to spend with each other. It’s a real privilege to see how much they have grown and developed as individuals and as a community during the most tumultuous times we have witnessed in generations.</p>

<p>Selfishly, it also meant that I had time with other adults who see the promise and purpose in giving up their time for these kids.</p>

<p>It is difficult to overstate just how very normal and understated the entire weekend was. These kids continue to grow up in a world that is so very different to that of my own youth and it is my firm belief that by providing them these opportunities is at least some route to normalcy.</p>

<div class="gallery" data-columns="1">
  <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0409.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0413.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0415.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0416.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0427.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0431.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0436.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/skicamp/IMG_0448.jpeg"&gt;
</code></pre></div>  </div>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m writing this post through a different lens than I would have done twenty-four hours ago.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winter Camping</title><link href="https://sub.haus/2022/02/02/Winter-Camping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Camping" /><published>2022-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/2022/02/02/Winter-Camping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sub.haus/2022/02/02/Winter-Camping/"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend saw us out at Water Valley towards the foothills for our annual Winter Camp. Of course, being as Albertan weather tends to be winter when it feels like it, it was actually colder back in our November ‘Fall’ camp than we experienced just. No problem though. -16C overnight was cool enough to warrant the ‘winter’ experience and sufficiently warm enough not to impact us from having to retain social separation and all that goes along with remaining on the science-side of managing our response to COVID.</p>

<p>Ice Safety was the core theme to the weekend, given we were sat at the side of a large enough lake to offer a great risk landscape.  We took to the ice with an auger and talked over ice thickness for weight support and signs to watch for in ice conditions. It’s always intersting to see confidence grow in the skills we teach from those who are maybe just that little more nervous about trying something new.</p>

<p>Having a smaller showing of participants actually made for a more effective camp given there was a good ratio of skilled and experienced folks to new and less experienced kids.</p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last weekend saw us out at Water Valley towards the foothills for our annual Winter Camp. Of course, being as Albertan weather tends to be winter when it feels like it, it was actually colder back in our November ‘Fall’ camp than we experienced just. No problem though. -16C overnight was cool enough to warrant the ‘winter’ experience and sufficiently warm enough not to impact us from having to retain social separation and all that goes along with remaining on the science-side of managing our response to COVID.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Back To The Future</title><link href="https://sub.haus/2022/02/01/Back-to-the-Future/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Back To The Future" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sub.haus/2022/02/01/Back-to-the-Future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sub.haus/2022/02/01/Back-to-the-Future/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve decided to resurrect the Breadedcod.com site after a fairly lengthy hiatus. I can’t even remember when the old Wordpress blog went by the wayside, but it’s quite some time ago. *I just checked, it’s been a few years according to the ol’ reliable of archive.org.</p>

<p>Anyway, ‘HI!’ again, for those of you who may have happened upon me before, and welcome to anyone else who might be here as a new reader or passive observer. Eye-rollers are also welcome. Even occasional tutters.</p>

<h4 id="reasons-to-be-digitally-cheerful">Reasons to be (digitally) cheerful.</h4>

<p>One of the main reasons for me to slap all this back together is because I’m so done with trying (and failing) to make Facebook or other social platforms actually work for me in a way that’s conducive to either getting things out of my head and on paper or in building positive relationships with new people.</p>

<p>All those social megavendors are just massive digital landfills to me now. I actually rejoined Facebook in a limited capacity because of the pandemic, after swearing off it and going dark. It feels like a mistake being back there. I love the fact I’m reconnected with some folks from my old friend list (although it is heavily curated now). The problems that were apparent a couple of years ago haven’t improved though. It feels even more polarised than ever. It’s almost like people are trapped in there and are trying desperately to keep going while ignoring the rot going on all around them.</p>

<p>I am going to sound incredibly old with all of this - likely because I <em>am</em>, in internet years at least. In those <em>old</em> days of the internet, I have met some truly amazing people. Some have become close friends and the opportunities that were opened up through meeting them changed my life. That’s what I hope to recapture here and hopefully help others find along the way too.</p>]]></content><author><name>Paul Hobson</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve decided to resurrect the Breadedcod.com site after a fairly lengthy hiatus. I can’t even remember when the old Wordpress blog went by the wayside, but it’s quite some time ago. *I just checked, it’s been a few years according to the ol’ reliable of archive.org.]]></summary></entry></feed>